Hello, and welcome back. We're going to be talking now about
大家好，欢迎回来。我们接下来讲
Wiener Filter. So we have to remember our basic
维纳滤波 所以我们必须记住我们在这儿看到的
degradation model that we see here. We have again, a filter basically
基础退化模型   我们又遇到了它 不过  像以前一样  一个大体上
blurring motion blur the focus as we have thought.
运动模糊的滤波会导致焦点模糊
And we have the noise and we discuss a lot about noise.
产生了噪点  我们就是要研究噪点
And then we observe this and we want to reconstruct an image from our
接下来我们观察噪点  我们试图从我们的观察中重建图像。
observation. And we're going to design a filter here
在这  我们要设计一个名为
called Wiener Flitering. That basically is going to help us to get
维纳滤波的滤波。 在特定情况下  维纳滤波会帮助我们得到
a very, very good restoration under certain conditions.
非常非常好的修复
The basic idea of Wiener Filtering is that we want to minimize the mean square
维纳滤波的基本思想是  我们尽可能使
root between the reconstruction and the original signal.
重建信号和原信号之间的均方根最小
So I'm going to write the mean square over.
所以我要写出方差
It's basically the expectation of the square of the error between the original
它基本上是原信号和重建信号
signal and the reconstructed signal. And we have talk a lot about this type of
之间的平方误差期望值 过去我们已经多次讲过这种类型的误差
error in the past. We have to square it and here it is so
我们要把它平方一下 就是这样了
it's the expectation of the square of the error.
从而它变成了平方误差的期望值
Now you may wonder but I don't know the original sigma.
到这你或许会想 我不知道原始西格玛值
That's the whole point of doing restoration it's just getting back to
修复的关键就是在于在不知道原信号的情况下得到
something which is like the original signal without knowing it.
它的近似值
But we have an expectation here. So don't need to know the original
但是我们已经有了期望值 所以我们没必要知道原始信号
signal. We just need to know some statistical
我们只需要知道原始信号的一些
characterization of the original signal. Now it's not hard to show that the filter
统计值特征 现在不难看出要用在这儿的滤波
to put here that will minimize this. We'll get the following form so basically
将会使它最小化 我们将得到下面的式子
the Fourier. Transform of the reconstruction of the
重构信号的傅立叶变换
reconstructed signal will be, and I am going to write it down and explain what I
我先写下来再解释下我写的东西
am writing. It's the conjugate of the filter, a
（它的傅里叶变换等于）滤波的共轭
complex conjugate of the Fourier transform of the filter that we have
也就是用之前视频中讲到的方法得到的
estimated as we have described in the previous videos, divided by basically the
滤波的傅里叶变换的复共轭
magnitude of this filter that we have estimated.
除以所估计的滤波的大小
So this is the degradation filter, plus the power spectrum, and don't worry, if
所以这是退化滤波 还有能量谱  不用担心
you don't know exactly what that means or if you forgot I'm going to remind you in
如果你记不清或者忘记了它是什么意思 稍后我会再次提示
a second. The power spectrum of the noise, divided by the power spectrum, of
噪声的能谱  除以这个信号的能谱
the signal, and all these multiplying our observation.
所有的这些乘以观测值
So, this is the Wiener Filter. It's a filter that is multiplying our
所以 这个是维纳滤波 它乘以我们观测值
observation to obtain the reconstruction and of course, we have to invert this,
得要重建的滤波 当然 我们要倒过来
the inverse Fourier to get the basic, the estimation.
逆傅里叶变换得到基本的 得到估计
So once again, what is this doing? This is minimizing the mean square error.
然后又一次 这是在做什么呢   这是在使均方差最小
I have to explain to you or remind you, what are these concepts?
我必须向你解释或者说提醒  这些概念是什么
But before that, if you want to know how do I get from
但在这之前  如果你想知道我如何
wanting to minimize the mean square error to this expression is actually not hard.
从最小均方差到这个表达式   这实际上不难
You can find a folderization for example in this Wikipedia page.
比如  你可以在这个维基页面中找到
It's truly not hard. You just write almost they say you write
这真的不难 你基本只要照着所说的写
the definition of the mean square error, the expectation, and we know that we need
均方差、期望的定义   并且我们知道在我们
to take derivatives when we are trying to minimize the function.
在求函数最小值的时求导
I knew very fast I'm going to go to this. So let's just explain again this
我很快就会讲到这个 所以就让我再次解释下这个
expression. Here is once again the complex conjugate
公式 在这儿又遇到了
of your Fourier response of the degradation filter. Here is basically the
退化滤波的傅里叶变换的共轭复数 这大致上是
magnitude square nothing has than that and here as I said this is the power
没有什么比大小平方  并且正像我说的这是能量谱，
spectrum so, of the noise and the power spectrum of your original signal or the
所以   噪点和原始信号的能量谱或者
signal class. The power spectrum is basically the
信号类   能谱大致上是
magnitude of the fourier transform, of the correlation function.
傅里叶变换和相关函数的量度
So you have F. F has a correlation function.
所以有了F F有相关函数
You take the Fourier transform of that. And you compute the magnitude of that,
你对他做傅里叶变换  你计算它的大小
and that's the power spectrum of the signal, and the same for the noise.
得到的结果就是这个信号的能量谱   对噪点来说也是一样的。
You take the noise, you compute a correlation of the noise, you take the
对噪点采样  计算出它的相关度  对
fully transformed. You compute the magnitude, that's the
它做完全变换 算出等级 就是
power spectrum so you don't need to know the function, you need to know the noise,
能量谱  所以你不必知道函数 你需要知道噪点
the exact function or the exact noise. You need to know some statistical
确切的函数或者确切的噪点  你需要知道它的一些
characterization of that. So this is the ideal Wiener Filter and of
统计学特征 所以这是理想的维纳滤波 当然
course you need to know this in order to be able to actually implement it.
为了你真正实现它  你需要知道了解这点。
So most of the time there's a very simple trick that is done instead of estimating
所以  大多数情况下有非常简便的窍门来计算  而不采用估计的方法。
this. This is basically replaced and I'm just going to use a different color.
这基本上会被替换 我想用个不同的颜色
This, all this expression, which is difficult
这些 所有的这些表达   都很难去
to estimate unless you know a lot of statistical characterizations of your
估算 除非你知道你信号的很多统计学特征
signal. This is basically replaced by a constant.
这基本上是被一个常数替代
Pretty surprising, isn't it? A very complicated thing is replaced by a
很惊讶吧   一个非常复杂的东西被一个常数
constant. So, I don't use this anymore, I basically
替代  所以 我再也不用它了 基本上我
go and replace this by a constant. And then, all I have to estimate is one
去用常数代替 接下来 我只需要估计一个数。
number. Assuming of course that I have already
当然假设 我已经
estimated the, degradation. The basic, the operation that produced a
估计了退化 基本上 像高斯或者产生
degradation like a Gaussian or like, the filter that produces motion blur.
运动模糊的滤波那样会产生降解的运算
So very simple operation. A very simple filter, with only one
所以非常简单的运算 仅有一个未知数的简单滤波
unknown, that can be estimated in a number of ways.
可以通过很多种方式估计
But we are not going to discuss that, now.
但是我们现在不准备讨论这个
It's basically similar to the way of that we needed to estimate the variance of the
它基本上与我们要估计高斯方差
Gaussian or how much motion blur there is in an image.
或是图像运动模糊程度的方法相似
It looks very similar, to the basic to the inverse filter.
它看上去和逆滤波非常相似
Remember in the inverse filter, all that we need is we actually took the degraded
记住 在逆滤波中 我们要做的是拿到退化图像
image, meaning the observation and we divided by basically the Fourier
也就是观测值 除以H的傅里叶变换
transform of H, basically this H that we see here.
基本上是我们这里看到的这样的H
And here is slightly different, similar but different.
这儿有些小小不同 相似但是有差别。
And that slight difference is critical as we're going to see in the next examples.
这些细微的差别是至关重要的 我们将会在下面的例子中看到。
So let's just look at these images. We have seen this image before.
让我们看看这些图片 我们以前看过这些图片
This is the original image, and this is basically the result of turbulence on
这是原始图片  这大概是对图像进行湍流处理
that image. And as we know and we discussed before,
后的结果  正如我们之前了解和讨论过的一样
this model basically with a Gaussian filter.
这个模型通常情况下使用高斯滤波
This is the result of inverse filtering, so we basically take the gaussian filter,
这是反滤波后的结果  所以我们基本上采用高斯滤波
we take the fourier transform and we divide this image, basically it's fourier
我们对它进行傅里叶变换 用这张图 也就是它的傅里叶变换
transform, we divide it by the fourier transform of the Gaussian and then we
除以高斯方法处理过的傅里叶变换
reconstruct. So this is nothing else done, taking this image,
再进行重建 没有别的事了 拿过这张图
taking its Fourier and dividing it, but by the Fourier Transform of a Gaussian.
对它进行傅里叶变换 除以高斯方法的傅里叶变换
And then inverting the Fourier of the result.
然后对结果进行逆傅里叶变换
And is, I would say, quite a bad result and we know why.
是的 我会说 确实是一个坏结果 我们都知道为什么
We're dividing, although the Gaussian memory goes to zero, it gets very small
我们在除的时候  虽然高斯不会等于零  但它的值会变得非常小
values. And that basically is enhancing a lot,
这大概上提高很多
and is making our reconstruction very, very nonstable.
使我们的重建非常非常不稳定
On the other hand, this is the result of the Wiener filtering.
另一方面说 这是维纳滤波的结果
I think its outstanding result so its basically what we just saw in the
我认为这是一个突出的成果 所以它大致上是我们在
previous slide we basically the filter is to have been one over the Gaussian as
以前的幻灯片上看到的  在这里成为了高斯滤波器
here, the filter basically is the conjugate over H^2 plus the constant.
滤波等于共轭除以H^2加常数
That's the filter that we apply to this image.
这是我们在这张图片上使用的滤波
We don't apply 1 over the Gaussian, or 1 / H.
我们在高斯滤波上不使用1    或者1/H
We apply this filter and we get that significantly better result.
我们用这个滤波得到了很好地结果
And the result here is illustrated with basically almost trial and error.
这儿的结果基本是通过不断试错得到的
We basically try the best possible K knowing the original, it's just for
我们尝试了最初知道的可能最好的K值
better logical reasons basically to show you how great we can get the result with
为了更好地有逻辑的原因  基本上是为了向你展示如果我们
Wiener filtering if we estimate this constant.
估计了常数值 能用维纳滤波能得多好的结果
So to show you that this is not, just not all one example that it can degrade,
为了让你看到这不是唯一能退化的例子
let's just show a second example of an image that we have seen before.
让我们再讲一个以前看过的图像
Here we have an image. It's based in the book, it's the cover of
有一张图像  它是我们用的这本书的封面
the book that we have been using but just in black and white.
只不过是黑白的
It has motion. We have seen that already, so it has
它有运动 我们已经看到了 所以它有
motion blur. And then we add to it noise.
运动模糊 接下来我们添加噪点
And then we apply, we know exactly a motion blur so we
接下来进行处理 我们准确地知道运动模糊 所以我们
computed exactly the filter and we apply inverse filter and this is what we get.
计算滤波的准确值  进行反滤波 这就是我们得到的结果
So once again going from here to here is the result of taking this image and
所以 又一次 从这到那是
filtering with an inverse filter, 1 / H. And I'm not including the problems that
把这个图像用逆滤波-1/H进行处理后的结果 我没有包括可能会发生的问题
might happen because I need to estimate age, I'm actually putting the exact age
因为我需要估计时间 事实上我把创建这个图像的具体时间
that I used to create this image and the result is close to a disaster basically
写下 ，结果由于同样的原因结果很糟糕
for the same reasons. As we saw in the previous example.
正如在之前的例子里看到的
This is the result of Wiener filtering, okay?
这是维纳滤波的结果 可以吗？
Once again, this is what we are applying here and
再来一次 这是我们这里的用的
again we use the best constant that we could use against for Pedagogic reasons
我们用教学中能用的最好的常数
to just rate the power of the inner filtering.
来评估内部滤波器的功率
Now, you probably see here the blur and you
现在 你可能看到污点和
might see also the noise. Here we actually take one order of
噪点 在这儿事实上我们取了一份
magnitude less noise. Same blur same motion blur and again we
更小数量级的噪点 同样的模糊 同样的运动模糊 我们再次
apply the inverse filter and we apply the Weiner.
应用逆滤波维纳
And again this is really, really bad. Basically what we are recovering here is
同样非常非常不好 基本上我们在这里恢复的
the motion. We are not able to recover anything else
是运动 其他的我们都不能恢复
but Weiner filtering is doing outstanding job.
但是维纳滤波效果非常好
If we reduce the noise even further, actually five orders of magnitude. I
如果我们进一步降低噪点 降五个数量级
don't think you can see any noise. If you compare this to this, basically
就什么噪点也看不到了 如果两者一比较
there is, the noise is so small, that basically the dominant degradation here
基本上是 噪点非常小 以至于优势降解是
is the motion blur. This is the inverse filter.
运动模糊 这就是逆滤波
Now, it's much better, but it's still not great.
现在好多了 但是仍不是非常好
Again, this is nothing else than an inverse filter.
再次 这只不过是一个逆滤波器
but applied, to the, to the blur and noisy image.
但是被应用到模糊和噪点的图像上
And this is the result of Wiener filter. So this column is always inverse.
这是维纳滤波的结果 这一列是逆滤波的结果
This column is always Wiener filtering. And just different levels of noise here.
这一列是维纳滤波 这里是不同程度的噪点
I think we've got the perfect result. Why it's perfect because as I say in this
我认为我们得到了完美的结果 为什么说完美 因为正如我在例子中说的一样
exampl, in this kind of artificial Pedagogic example we didn't have to
在这种人工设计出教学示例中我们不必
estimate H, we know exactly H and also we estimated the best possible K.
估计H  我们知道H 我们估计出最合适的K
But this illustrates how this filter is extremely powerful once we estimate the
但这说明这个滤波非常强大
degradation filter or the motion blur in this case, and the constant.
只要我们估计出退化滤波或是运动模糊 以及常数
And still, filter inverse filter. Sorry,
而滤波逆滤波 很抱歉
here even if we know exactly H, it just doesn't do a good job.
我们即使知道准确的H值 它也不太好使
So I hope I convinced you that Wiener filtering is a very simple operation, and
所以我想让你了解维纳滤波是一个非常简单的函数
it can be extremely, extremely powerful. So by this we conclude Wiener filtering
它可以非常非常强大 所以这里我们结束了维纳滤波部分
and in the next video we are going to just basically conclude the unit on
在接下来的视频中我们将要基本上结束修复单元
restoration. Thank you very much.
非常感谢